Guide to the Boris Moiseevich Sapir Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Arranged Manuscripts
  - Denike, George "Men'sheviki v 1917 g." (Box 12)
  - "Posle razgona Uchreditel'nogo sobraniia" (Box 13)
  - Gershuni, Jacques Malinovsky (Box 13)
  - Fel'shtinskii, IUrii (1956-) "Razgovory s Bukharinym" (Box 13)
  - Getzler, Israel (1920-) "Martov in 1917;" "The Mensheviks, a Post Mortem" (Box 13)
  - Gurevich, Boris L'vovich [Dvinov] "Moskovskii sovet rabochikh deputatov" (Box 13)
  - "Pervaia mirovaia voina i Rossiiskaiasotsialdemokratiia", (5 folders) (Box 13)
  - "Shtrikhi moei zhizni" (Box 13)
  - Janouch, Frantisek "A Voluntary Trip to Siberia" (Box 14)
  - "Report on a Trip... 1988" (Box 14)
  - Lande, Leo "Men'shevizm v 1917 g.", (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Research notes (Box 14)
  - Levin, N. "Vospominaniia", (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Liebich, Andre (1948-) "Marxism and Totalitarianism" (Box 15)
  - Mozer, Alfred "Eine Reisebericht, U.S.A. 1960" (Box 15)
  - Nicolaevsky, Boris I. (1887-1966) "Gruppa sibirskikh tsimmerval'distov" (Box 15)
  - "RSDRP (men'sheviki) ... s dekabriia 1917 po iiul' 1918" (Box 15)
  - "Men'shevizm v period voennogo kommunizma" (Box 15)
  - Pipes, Richard "Russian Marxism and Its Populist Background" (Box 15)
  - Pospielovsky, Dimitry (1935-) "The Role of Ethics in History" (Box 15)
  - Sapir, Boris "Die Arbeitsvertrag nach dem Entwurfe eines allgemeinen Arbeitsvertragsgesetzes" (Box 15)
  - "The Displaced Jews" (Box 15)
  - "Entstehung und Entwicklungsprozess der juedischen Kolonie in Kuba", (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - "Fedor Il'ich Dan i ego poslednaia kniga" (Box 15)
  - "Jewish Socialists around 'Vpered'" (Box 15)
  - "Die jugendlichen Arbeiter in Russland" (Box 15)
  - "The Last Chapter" (Box 15)
  - "Liberman i russkii sotsializm" (Box 15)
  - Sapir, Boris On Dostoevskii (Box 16)
  - On Solovki (Box 16)
  - "Origin and Growth of the Jewish Community in Cuba" (Box 16)
  - "Poslednaia glava" (Box 16)
  - "Predshestvenniki men'shevizma" (Box 16)
  - "Sobiranie materialov po istorii evreev v Kube..." (Box 16)
  - "Die Staatsschuldenproblem und die Klassiker" (Box 16)
  - "Study of the History of the Menshevik Party" (Box 16)
  - "An Unknown Correspondent of Andrey Bely" (Box 16)
  - "V okkupirovanoi Gollandii" (Box 16)
  - Schwartz, Solomon Meierovich "Komissiia Shidlovskogo" (Box 16)
  - "Men'shevizm i bol'shevizm v ikh otnoshenii k massovomu rabochemu dvizheniiu" (Box 16)
  - Volin, Semen IUlevich [Wolin] "Deiatel'nost' men'shevikov v profsoiuzakh..." (Box 16)
  - "Men'shevizm v 20-kh i nachale 30-kh gg.", (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Welcker, J.M. "Zwischen Wirklichkeit und Traum" (Box 17)
  - Windsburg, Benjamin "Last Days of the Gush Etzion Field Hospital" (Box 17)
  - Unidentified authors (Box 17)
  - Sapir's notebooks, (16 items) (Box 18)
  - Sapir's notebooks, (10 items and assorted loose papers) (Box 19)
  - Sapir's miscellaneous notes and short essays, (5 folders) (Box 19)
  - Sapir's notes and photocopies in binders (chiefly on Russian Marxism, populism and early socialism), (7 items) (Box 20)
  - Sapir's notes and photocopies in binders (chiefly on Russian Marxism, populism and early socialism), (5 items) (Box 21)
  - Sapir's notes and photocopies in binders (chiefly on Russian Marxism, populism and early socialism), (8 items) (Box 22)
- Series IV: Subject Files
  - American Joint Jewish Distribution Committee JDC Primer, 1945 (Box 23)
  - Minutes ... of Department Heads' Meetings, 1966-75 (Box 23)
  - "Arkhiv Aksel'roda IISH (International Institute for Social History)" A collection of typed transcripts and letters to and from P.B. (Pavel Borisovich Aksel'rod (1850-1928), 1901-1920 (Box 24)
  - Aksel'rod On Potresov's "V plenu u illiuzii" (Box 24)
  - Aksel'rod Letters to Dan F. [Fedor], 1871-1947 (Box 24)
  - Aksel'rod To Dan and Trotsky (1879-1940) (Box 24)
  - Aksel'rod To Garvi, Petr A. (Petr Abramovich), 1881-1944 (Box 24)
  - Aksel'rod To "Zhizn'" (Box 24)
  - Bliumenfel'd, I.S. Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Broido, E.L. Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Chkhenkeli, A.I. Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Ermolaev, K.M. Letters to Dan (Box 24)
  - Ezhov, Sergei Osipovich Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Garvi, Petr A. (Petr Abramovich) (1881-1944) Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Garvi, Petr A. To Martov, L, 1873-1923 (Box 24)
  - Kalafati, D.P. Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Levitskii, V.O. [Tsederbaum] Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Maevskii, E. Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Maiskii, I.M. (Ivan Mikhailovich) (1884-1975) Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Maiskii, I.M. (Ivan Mikhailovich) (1884-1975) To Martov (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 24)
  - Piletskii, IA. A. Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Potresov, A.N. (Aleksandr Nikolaevich) (1869-1934) Letters to Martov (Box 24)
  - Rakovskii, Khristian Georgievich (1873-1941) Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Roshchin Letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Schwartz, Solomon Meierovich letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Semkovskii, S. letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Valetskii, Maks letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
  - Viaz'menskii, G.M. & Bebutov, D.I., Kniaz letters to Aksel'rod (Box 24)
- Series V: Biographical Series
  - Abramovitch, Raphael A. (Box 25)
  - Aksel'rod, P.B.(Pavel Borisovich) (1850-1928) (Box 25)
  - Aleksandrova, Vera (1895-1966) (Box 25)
  - Aronson, Gregor (1887-1968) (Box 25)
  - Dallin, David J. (1889-1962) (Box 25)
  - Dan, F. (Fedor) (1871-1947) (Box 25)
  - Dan, Lidiia (Box 25)
  - Denike, George (Box 25)
  - Gurevich, Boris L'vovich (Box 25)
  - Kammermacher, Julia (Box 25)
  - Lande, Leo (Box 25)
  - Lopatin, G.A. (Box 25)
  - Martov, L. (1873-1923) (Box 26)
  - Meijer, Jan Marinus (Box 26)
  - Nicolaevsky, Boris I. (1887-1966) (Box 26)
  - Schapiro, Leonard Bertram (1908-) (Box 26)
  - Schwartz, Solomon Meierovich (Box 26)
  - Shub, David A. (Box 26)
  - Souvarine, Boris (Box 26)
  - Svirskaia, Mina L'vovna (Box 26)
  - TSereteli, I.G. (Iraklii Georgievich) (1881-1959) (Box 26)
  - Woytinsky, Wladimir S. & Emma (Box 26)
- Series VI: History of Menshevism Project
  - Biografii men'shevikov, (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - Contribution by Leo Lande (Box 27)
  - Copies of resolutions, etc., 1917 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence with Leopold H. Haimson (Box 27)
  - Obituaries, (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - Proposals, plans, drafts, (3 folders) (Box 27)
- Series VII: Numbered files on Populism
  Typed transcripts of correspondence, clippings and notes
  - Aleksandrov, V.M. (1) (Box 28)
  - Anderson, F.N. (2) (Box 28)
  - Armashevskii, P.Ia. (3) (Box 28)
  - Aronzon, M. (4) (Box 28)
  - "Beverlei" (5) (Box 28)
  - Munich library (6) (Box 28)
  - Zurich library (7) (Box 28)
  - Brovkov, A.P. (8) (Box 28)
  - Buturlin, Aleksandr Sergeevich (1845-1916) (9) (Box 28)
  - Vainer, L. (10) (Box 28)
  - Vaisman, Boris Abramovich (11) (Box 28)
  - Varzar, V.E. (Vasilii Egorovich) (1851-1940) (12) (Box 28)
  - "Vpered" (13-15) (Box 28)
  - Ginzburg, L.S. (16-17) (Box 28)
  - Glasko, I.A. (18) (Box 28)
  - Golubov, Natan (19) (Box 28)
  - Gol'denberg, Latar' Borisovich (20) (Box 28)
  - "Grazhdanin" (21) (Box 28)
  - Gurevich, G.E. (22) (Box 28)
  - Dalgat (23) (Box 28)
  - Denike, Iosif Egorovich (24) (Box 28)
  - Dekhterev, V.G. [Morozov] (25) (Box 28)
  - Drizo, Aleksandr Akimovich (26-27) (Box 28)
  - Zaslavskii, Evgenii Osipovich (28) (Box 28)
  - Zdanovich, Georgii Feliksovich [Petrov] (29) (Box 29)
  - "Zemlia i volia" (29a) (Box 29)
  - Zubku-Kodreanu, N.P. (30) (Box 29)
  - Zundelevich, A.I. (31-32) (Box 29)
  - Ivanchin-Pisarev, A.I. (33) (Box 29)
  - Idel'son, R.Kh. (34) (Box 29)
  - Il'in, Vasilii Mikhailovich (35) (Box 29)
  - Jochelson, Waldemar, [Iokel'son] (1855-1937) (Box 29)
  - Karganova, L.A. (37) (Box 29)
  - Karpov, Valerian Porfirovich [Federov] (38) (Box 29)
  - Kviatkovskii, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich (38a) (Box 29)
  - Klaver (39) (Box 29)
  - Klements, D.A. (40) (Box 29)
  - Kobylianskii, Erast Aleksandrovich (41) (Box 29)
  - Koval'skii, Ivan Martynovich (42) (Box 29)
  - Kropotkin, Aleksandr Alekseevich (43) (Box 29)
  - Kuliadko-Koretskii, Aleksandr Grigor'evich (44) (Box 29)
  - Kuliadko-Koretskii, Nikolai Grigor'evich (45) (Box 29)
  - Lavrov, P.L. (Petr Lavrovich) (1823-1900) (46) (Box 29)
  - Lakier, E. (47) (Box 29)
  - Lin'v, Aleksandr Longinovich (48) (Box 29)
  - Linev, Ivan Longinovich (49) (Box 29)
  - Lytkin, Dmitrii (50) (Box 29)
  - Mandelbaum, A. (51) (Box 29)
  - Margolin, Moisei Isakovich [Moiseev] (52) (Box 29)
  - Melenchuk, Vasilii Sil'vestrovich (53) (Box 29)
  - Natanson, Mark Andreevich (1851-1919) (Box 30)
  - "Nachalo" (54a) (Box 30)
  - Nikiforov, Lev Pavlovich? (55) (Box 30)
  - "Obshchina" (56) (Box 30)
  - Pavlovskii, Aaron IAkovlevich (57) (Box 30)
  - Pereiaslovtseva, Sof'ia Mikhailovna (58) (Box 30)
  - Podolinskii, S.A. (Box 30)
  - "Rabotnik" (58a) (Box 30)
  - Rennekamp, S.F. (59) (Box 30)
  - Rikhter, Dmitrii Ivanovich (60) (Box 30)
  - Romm, Maksim (61) (Box 30)
  - Riabinov (62) (Box 30)
  - Sazhin, Mikhail Petrovich (63) (Box 30)
  - Saper, Grigorii Davidovich (64) (Box 30)
  - Smirnov, Valerian Nikolaevich (65) (Box 30)
  - Solov'ev, P. (66) (Box 30)
  - Staroborskii, A.S. (67) (Box 30)
  - Stepanov (68) (Box 30)
  - Sudzalovskii, N.K. (69) (Box 30)
  - Takin, AntonFeliksovich (70) (Box 30)
  - Tveritinov, A.N. (71) (Box 30)
  - "Travailleur" (71a) (Box 30)
  - Tumanov, S.B. (72) (Box 30)
  - Turskii (73) (Box 30)
  - Finkel'shtein, A. (74) (Box 30)
  - "Frichi" (75) (Box 30)
  - Tsimmerman, Emilii Emil'evich (76) (Box 30)
  - Chaikovskii, N.V. (Nikolai Vasilevich) (1850-1926) (Box 30)
  - Chudnovskii, I.L. (78) (Box 30)
  - Shtakov, Vladimir Semenovich (79) (Box 30)
  - Shnee, Samuil Abramovich (79a) (Box 30)
  - Elpidin, M.K. (80) (Box 30)
  - El'snits, Aleksandr Leont'evich (81) (Box 30)
  - Epshtein, Anna Mikhailovich (82) (Box 30)
  - Ianvyn, Mikhail Ivanovich [Kapitan] (83) (Box 30)
  - Varia (84) (Box 30)
- Series VIII: Populism P.L. (Petr Lavrovich) Lavrov & "Vpered"
  - "Arkhiv Smirnova" (Box 31)
  - Copies from "Arkhiv P.S.-R." (Box 31)
  - Dekhterev-Morozov Manuscripts and letters (Box 31)
  - "Lavrov and the commune of Paris" (Box 31)
  - "Lavrov and Tkachev" (Box 31)
  - Lavrov to Valerian Nikolaevich Smirnov, (Typed transcripts of letters) (Box 31)
  - Lavrov, P.L. to R.KH. Idel'son and Valerian Nikolaevich Smirnov, (Notecards with quotations from letters) (Box 31)
  - "Nenapechatannye materialy iz arkhiva 'Vpered'" (Box 31)
  - "Opis' arkhiva P.S.-R." (Box 31)
  - "Predrassudki nashikh sotsial'nykh revoliutsionerov protiv Evreev" (Box 31)
  - Voshchakin, Iakov V. To Valerian Nikolevich Smirnov (Box 31)
  - "Vpered!Neperiodicheskii sbornik" (Box 31)
  - Populism and Lavrov, (, Miscellaneous notes, photocopies and transcripts of letters - (loose notecards and folders 1-7)) (Box 32)
  - Populism and Lavrov, (Folders 8-17 ) (Box 33)
- Series IX: Miscellaneous Topics
  - "Arkhiv Samuel Efimovich Estrina" (Box 34)
  - Berlin, Isaiah, Sir (Box 34)
  - Bolsheviks (Box 34)
  - "Dvizhenie upolnomochennykh 1918" (Box 34)
  - Early Russian Socialism, (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Emigration (Box 34)
  - Emigre Mensheviks and 2nd Emigration (Box 34)
  - Esenin, Sergei Aleksandrovich (1895-1925) (Box 34)
  - General history (Box 35)
  - Goldenberg, Boris (Box 35)
  - Goldman, Emma (1869-1940) (Box 35)
  - Heller, M.Ia. (Box 35)
  - History of "Sotsialisticheskii Vestnik" and Social Democrats (Box 35)
  - IAkir, Petr Ionovich (Box 35)
  - International Institute for Social History (Box 35)
  - IISH materials on Russian Social Democracy (Box 35)
  - Iz arkhiva red. "Sots. Vestnika" (Box 35)
  - Jansen, Marc "Show Trial under Lenin" (Box 36)
  - Jewish Bund (Box 36)
  - Jews in Cuba (Box 36)
  - Jews (miscellaneous) (Box 36)
  - Korolenko, Vladimir Galaktionovich (1853-1921) (Box 36)
  - Kronshtadt uprising (article) (Box 36)
  - Michael Confino Kropotkin, Petr (Box 36)
  - Kuskova, Ektarina Dmitrievna (Box 36)
  - League for Russian Freedom, 1949, 1950, 1951 (Box 37)
  - Lenin (Box 37)
  - Leo Lande's work with ORT (Box 37)
  - LŸbbe, Peter ed., "Kautsky gegen Lenin" (Box 37)
  - Luxemburg, Rosa (1871-1919) (Box 37)
  - Marx and Marxism (Box 37)
  - Materials received from A. Kimball, ca. 1970 (Box 37)
  - Materials received from L. Kisselgoff, 1984 (Box 37)
  - "Miles" (Kurt Menz, Walter Lowe) (Box 37)
  - Mishkinsky, Moshe (1917-) (Box 37)
  - Nechaev and "Kolokol" (Box 37)
  - "Osvobozhdenie Truda" (Box 37)
  - Paris Commune (Box 38)
  - Pollak, Oscar, and Marianne Austrian socialism (Box 38)
  - "Protiv techeniia" and disagreements among NY mensheviks (Box 38)
  - "Rabochaia Mysl'," 1898 (Box 38)
  - Raeff, Marc (Box 38)
  - Reviews of and responses to Boris Sapir's publications, (2 folders) (Box 38)
  - Russian 1917 Revolution and Civil War (Box 38)
  - Russian culture, philosophy, etc. (Box 38)
  - Russian Social Democracy, (4 folders) (Box 39)
  - Sapir, Boris "Bibliografie van de werken van B.M. Sapir" by Marc Jansen (Box 39)
  - Sapir, Boris Biographical material (miscellaneous) (Box 39)
  - Sapir, Boris Obituaries (Box 39)
  - Sapir in Denmark, 1930 (Box 39)
  - Sapir's exchange with Isaac Deutscher over Menshevism, 1965 (Box 39)
  - Sapir's flight from Europe, 1940-43 (Box 39)
  - Sapir's "Rehabilitation", 1991 (Box 39)
  - Sapir's trip to Europe, 1947 (Box 39)
  - Socialist movement in Soviet Russia, 1980s (Box 39)
  - Socialist Revolutionaries (Box 39)
  - Soiuz bor'by za osvobozhdenie narodov Rossii, 1948-49; 1950 (Box 40)
  - "Sotsialisticheskii Vestnik", 1940s & 1950s (Box 40)
  - Starink, Laura (Box 40)
  - Stalin (Box 40)
  - "Stikhi saratovskikh poetov" (Box 40)
  - Talin, V.I., 1880-1944 (Box 40)
  - Totalitarianism and "1984" (Box 40)
  - Trotsky, Leon (1879-1940) (Box 40)
  - Trotsky's correspondence with his wife, 1930s, (Photocopies of typed transcripts) (Box 40)
  - Wiedijk, C.H. "Koos Vorrink" (Box 41)
  - World socialism, 1980s, (2 folders) (Box 41)
  - Yivo Research Conference on Jewish Participation in Movements devoted to the Cause of Social Progress, 1964 (Box 41)
  - Zagorskii, S. (Box 41)
  - Zasulich, Vera Ivanovna (1849-1919) (Box 41)
- Series X: Photographs
  - Abramovitch, Raphael A. (Box 42)
  - Adler family (Box 42)
  - Aksel'rod, Aleksandr Pavlovich (Box 42)
  - Amal'rik, Andrei (1938-) (Box 42)
  - Andler family (Box 42)
  - Arkavina, Vera IAkovlevna (Box 42)
  - Aronson family (Box 42)
  - Baturskii, B.S. (Box 42)
  - Bauer, Otto (1881-1938) (Box 42)
  - Ber, Boris Naumovich (Box 42)
  - Bienstock, Gregory (1885-1954) (Box 42)
  - Blit, Lucjan (Box 42)
  - Bogdanov family (Box 42)
  - Bronshtein, Mikhail Adamovich (Box 42)
  - Brouckre, Louis de (1870-1951) (Box 42)
  - Caffi, Andreas (Box 42)
  - Chlenov, Boris Arkad'evich (Box 42)
  - Ciliga, P. (Box 42)
  - Dallin, David J. & L. (Box 42)
  - Dallin family (Box 42)
  - Denike, George (Box 42)
  - Dubua, Anatolii Edgardovich [Dubois] (Box 42)
  - Elias, Norbert (Box 42)
  - Erlich, Alexander (Box 42)
  - Ermolaev, Konstantin Mikhailovich (Box 42)
  - Estrin, Samuel Efimovich (Box 42)
  - Ezerskaia, F. (Box 42)
  - Garvi, Petr A. (Petr Abramovich) (1881-1944) and Sofiia (Box 42)
  - Getzler, Israel (1920-) (Box 42)
  - Ginzberg, Rafail IAkovlevich (Box 42)
  - Gofenberg, Iosif (Box 42)
  - Goldenberg, Boris (Box 42)
  - Grinfel'd, Iu.A. (Box 42)
  - Gringauz, Samuel (Box 42)
  - Gumbel, Emil Julius (1891-) (Box 42)
  - Gurevich, Sof'ia Il'ianovna (Box 42)
  - Heine, Fritz (Box 42)
  - Herzen monuments (Box 42)
  - Ingerman, Sergei Mikhailovich (Box 42)
  - International Socialist Congress, Vienna, 1931 (Box 42)
  - Isuv, Iosif Andreevich (Box 42)
  - Iudin, Isai L'vovich [Aizenstadt] (Box 42)
  - Iugov, A.A. (Box 42)
  - Iushkevich, Pavel Solomonovich (Box 42)
  - Jewish Labor Comittee (U.S.) (Box 42)
  - Jordan, Charles (Box 42)
  - Kalnnins, Bruno (Box 42)
  - Kammermacher, Julia, & M. Kefali (Box 42)
  - Kautsky family (Box 42)
  - Khundadze, Mikhail (Box 42)
  - Kranikhfel'd, Andrei Sergeevich (Box 42)
  - Krivinskaia, Anna Leopol'dovna (Box 42)
  - Kuchin family (Box 42)
  - Kun, Mikl-s, and Gerebon, Agnes (Box 42)
  - Kushev, Evgenii Igorevich (Box 42)
  - Kuskova, Ekaterina Dmitrievna (Box 42)
  - Lande, Leo (Box 43)
  - Landysheva, Evgeniia Aleksandrovna (Box 43)
  - Latvian Social Democrats (Box 43)
  - Lavrova, Antonia Khristoforovna (Box 43)
  - Levinsky, Eva (Box 43)
  - Litkens family (Box 43)
  - Lodyzhenskii, IUrii Il'ich (Box 43)
  - Lopatin, German Aleksandrovich (Box 43)
  - Makadziub, Ida Solomonovna and M. (Box 43)
  - Mandel'shtam, Maksim Osipovich (Box 43)
  - Menshevik graves (Box 43)
  - Menshevik groups (Box 43)
  - Mensheviks in Berlin, 1920s (Box 43)
  - Mensheviks in New York (Box 43)
  - Mering, Berta Borisovna (Box 43)
  - Minkoff, I. (Box 43)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 43)
  - Negreskul, Maria Petrovna (Box 43)
  - Nicolaevsky, Boris I. (1887-1966) (Box 43)
  - Norton, Barbara (Box 43)
  - Novakovskii, IAkov Solomonovich (Box 43)
  - Olberg, Paul (Box 43)
  - Ollenhauer, Erich (1901-1965) (Box 43)
  - Ossorguine-Bakounine, Tatiana (Box 43)
  - Panina, Sofiia Vladimirovna, Grafinia (1871-1956) (Box 43)
  - Picture postcards of socialists (Box 43)
  - Pop, Adelaida (Box 43)
  - Potresov, A.N. (Aleksandr Nikolaevich), 1869-1934 (Box 43)
  - Rabinovich, I.G. (Iosif Genrikhovich) and P.A. (Petr Abramovich) Garvi (Box 43)
  - Rozanov, V.N. (Box 43)
  - Rozenfel'd, Orest Ivanovich (Box 43)
  - Rubinstein, Nina (Box 43)
  - Rubinstein, T. (Box 43)
  - Sapir, Boris, family, & colleagues, (2 folders) (Box 43)
  - Sapir, Boris, Heidelberg, 1928-1931 (Box 43)
  - Schwartz, Solomon Meierovich (Box 44)
  - Shtein, Aleksandr N. (Box 44)
  - Silberner, Edmund (Box 44)
  - Skomorovskii, B.A. (Box 44)
  - Souvarine, Boris (Box 44)
  - Svirskaia, Mina L'vovna (Box 44)
  - Tabachnik, Mark I. (Box 44)
  - Tsederbaum family - L. Martov (Box 44)
  - Tsederbaum family - Sergei Osipovich Ezhov (Box 44)
  - Tsederbaum family- V.O. Levitskii (Box 44)
  - TSereteli, I.G. (Iraklii Georgievich) (1881-1959) (Box 44)
  - Tuchapskii, Pavel Lukich (Box 44)
  - Vainshtein, V.S. (Box 44)
  - Vasil'ev, Boris Stepanovich (Box 44)
  - Vigderzon, August L. (Box 44)
  - Volin, Semen IUl'evich (Box 44)
  - Vorrink, Koos (1891-1955) (Box 44)
  - Woytinsky, Wladimir S. (Box 44)
  - Yakobson, Sergius (1901-) (Box 44)
  - Zborovskii, Mikhail Solomonovich (Box 44)
  - Photos from Abramovitch family:from Lidiia Dan (2 folders) --From Sofiia Garvi --From B.A. Kalchen --From T. Rubinstein (Box 44)
- Series XI: Printed
  - Miscellaneous clippings, offprints, fliers, booklets, journals, ephemera. (Box 45-46)
- Series XII: Papers of Raphael A. Abramovitch (1880-1963)
  - Subseries XII.1: Cataloged Correspondence
    - Cahan, Abraham (1860-1951) To Raphael A. Abramovich, New York, [n.d.] & Feb. 1937 - Jan. 1938, (1 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s., 8 telegrams) (Box 47)
    - Dan, F. (Fedor) (1871-1947) To Raphael A. Abramovich, Issy-les-Moulineaux and Saint-Nizier-du-Moucherotte France, 15 Sept. 1936 and 10 July 1957, (2 a.l.s. (with carbon reply)) (Box 47)
    - Goldman, Emma (1869-1940) To Raphael A. Abramovich, Paris, 6 Aug. 1937 & 12 Aug. 1937, (2 autograph letters signed (with carbon replies)) (Box 47)
    - Kautsky, Karl (1854-1938) To Raphael A. Abramovich, Vienna, 5 March & 4 April 1947, (2 autograph letters signed) (Box 47)
    - Thomas, Norman (1884-1968) To Raphael A. Abramovich, New York, March - Nov. 1937, (4 typed letters signed (with carbon reply)) (Box 47)
  - Subseries XII.2: Arranged Correspondence
    - Correspondence and clippings concerning the disappearance of Abramovitch's son Mark Rein in 1937 (Box 47)
    - Rein Case - Numbered files 1a-1e. (Box 47)
    - Rein case - numbered files 2-11 (Box 48)
- Series XIII: Papers of Gregor Aronson (1887-1968)
  - Subseries XIII.1: Cataloged Correspondence
    - Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich (1886-1957) To Gregor Aronson, [v.p.], 1941-1957, (1 a.l.s., 19 t.l.s.) (Box 49)
    - Chagall, Marc (1887-) To Gregor Aronson, [v.p.], [n.d.] & 1945-1955, (5 autograph letters signed (photocopies)) (Box 49)
    - Karpovich, Michael, (1888-1959) To Gregor Aronson, [v.p.], 1946-1959, (24 a.l.s., 8 t.l.s., 1 a.p.c.s.) (Box 49)
    - Struve, Gleb To Gregor Aronson, BerkeleyCa., 5 Jan. 1960, (1 t.l.s. (with envelope)) (Box 49)
  - Subseries XIII.2: Arranged Correspondence
    - Aronson, Gregor (1887-1968) To various people (Box 49)
    - Kliachko, Konstantin & V. [Klatchko, C.] (Box 49)
    - Kuskova, Ekaterina Dmitrievna (Box 49)
    - Mel'gunov, S.P. (Sergei Petrovich) (1879-1956) (Box 49)
    - Nicolaevsky, Boris I. (1887-1966) (Box 49)
    - Shchupak, S. (Box 49)
    - Soloveichik, Samson (1930-) (Box 49)
    - Vol'skii, N.V., To Aronson - typed transcripts of letters to various people (Box 49)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 49)
  - Subseries XIII.3: Arranged Manuscripts
    - Aronson, Gregor "Evreiskii vopros v epokhu Stalina" (Box 50)
    - "Iz vospominanii provintsial'nogo zhurnalista" (Box 50)
    - "Kommentarii o rukopisi Aronson-Nikolaevskii" (Box 50)
    - "Masons in Russian Politics" (Box 50)
    - Miscellaneous notes, short essays, etc., (4 folders) (Box 50)
    - On emigration (Box 50)
    - On Jewish topics (Box 50)
    - On literature (Box 50)
    - On "party themes" (Box 50)
    - Aronson, Gregor On "various themes", (3 folders) (Box 51)
    - Poems (Box 51)
    - "Revoliutsionnaia iunost'" (Box 51)
    - "Right Menshevism" (Box 51)
    - "Tvorchestvo M.A. Aldanova" (Box 51)
    - "Zamechatel'nye liudi russkoi emigratsii" (Box 51)
    - "Zapiski sekretaria ORT-a" (Box 51)
    - Aronson, Gregor Notebooks, (10 items ) (Box 52)
    - Basil, John D. "Menshevik Foreign Policy in 1917" (Box 52)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 52)
    - Aronson, Gregor Documents (migration, citizenship, etc.) (Box 52)
    - Subject files:Biographies of Mensheviks (Box 52)
    - Subject files: Deaths of Anna and Gregor Aronson (Box 52)
    - Subject files: "Focus on Soviet Jewry" (Box 52)
    - Subject files: Mensheviks in emigration (Box 52)
    - Subject files: Menshevism History Project (Box 52)
    - Subject files: Reviews of Aronson's "Rossiia v epokhu revoliutsii" (Box 52)
    - Subject files: Russian emigre politics (Box 52)
- Series XIV: Papers of F. (Fedor) (1871-1947) and Lidiia Dan
  - Subseries XIV.1: Cataloged Correspondence
    - Blum, Leon (1872-1950) To [F. Dan?], Paris, [n.d.] & Aug. 1940?, (2 a.l.s. (photocopies; one signed with initials only)) (Box 53)
    - Dan, F. (Fedor) (1871-1947) To Berta Borisovna Mering, Berlin, 1924-1932, (3 a.p.c.s.) (Box 53)
    - Dan, F. (Fedor) (1871-1947) To Lidiia Dan, various places, 1940-1945, (5 a.l.s., 4 a.p.c.s.) (Box 53)
    - Dan, F. (Fedor) (1871-1947) To P.Z. Ivlev [Levinson], various places, 1940-1946, (23 a.l.s., 2 t.l.s., 5 a.p.c.s.) (Box 53)
  - Subseries XIV.2: Arranged Correspondence
    - Adler, Ekaterina IA. Various people to her (Box 53)
    - Adler, Friedrich (Box 53)
    - Balabanova, Angelica (Box 53)
    - Dan To P.B. (Pavel Borisovich) Aksel'rod, (copies) (Box 53)
    - Dan To A.N. (Aleksandr Nikolaevich) Potresov, (copies) (Box 53)
    - Dan, Lidiia To various people (Box 53)
    - To Ekaterina IA. Adler (Box 53)
    - To Gregor Aronson, (2 folders ) (Box 53)
    - To F. (Fedor) Dan (Box 53)
    - To Samuel Efimovich Estrin (Box 53)
    - To Nina Rubinshtein (Box 53)
    - Elkin, Boris I. (Box 53)
    - Heroys, H. (Box 53)
    - IUgov, A.A. [Yugow] (Box 53)
    - Kuskova, Ekaterina Dmitrievna (excerpts) (Box 53)
    - Meiksins, Gregory (Box 53)
    - Rozenfel'd, Orest Ivanovich (Box 53)
    - Vol'skii, N. V. (excerpts) (Box 53)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 53)
  - Subseries XIV.3: Arranged Manuscripts
    - Dan, F. (Fedor) Miscellaneous notes;Notebooks and Notes for "Novyi Put'" (Box 54)